Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that eight threads of
saffron a day can improve visual acuity
in older adults with mild or moderate
age-related macular degeneration?
Here’s the first story.
In addition to two
to three daily servings
of green leafy vegetables,
berries are considered
a healthy choice
for the preservation
of eye health.
As we age, our critical
retinal pigment epithelium layer
starts to break down.
However, we may be able
to decelerate that aging
with blueberries.
Human RPE cells bathed in
blueberry anthocyanins
had fewer free radicals
and a lower proportion
of aged cells,
suggesting that blueberries
and other red, blue, and purple
pigmented fruits and vegetables
may help prevent age-related
macular degeneration.
Protective properties
have also been demonstrated
in vitro on RPE cells
from purple
sweet potato anthocyanin
as well as the yellow pigment
in turmeric and an amla extract
(Indian gooseberry).
However, the only
human interventional trials
on berries for vision
were a month-long trial
of a bilberry extract
that demonstrated
significantly less eye strain
after iPad use
compared to placebo
and a study showing
three weeks of blueberry juice
or freeze-dried blueberry powder
both significantly improved
photostress recovery time,
which is the time needed
to recuperate visual acuity
after bright light exposure
by about five seconds.
Only one pigmented food
has been put to the test
in macular
degeneration patients:
the spice saffron.
Saffron is so potent
that the whole spice
can be stuffed into capsules
to pit them head-to-head
against placebo.
Those with early-stage
age-related macular degeneration
were randomized to a tiny pinch
(20 mg, about 8 threads)
of saffron versus placebo
for three months.
Compared to the placebo group,
the saffron group experienced
a significant improvement
in retinal flicker sensitivity--
that’s our ability to pick out
high frequency light pulses
(rather than seeing
the flickering light
as a steady beam)
that diminishes with age.
It’s a sensitive test
of retinal function,
but it is of questionable
clinical value.
However, there was
a small improvement
in visual acuity in 80 percent
of the saffron subjects
(being able to see one line
further down on an eye chart)
versus none improving
in the placebo group.
This is particularly important
for those with age-related
macular degeneration
for whom vision tends
to get worse over time,
not better.
What about a more
substantial pinch?
(50 mg, about 20 threads)
Compared to placebo,
three months of this larger dose
led to a similar
improvement in visual acuity
in macular degeneration
patients, suggesting more
is not necessarily better.
Saffron is the most
expensive spice there is,
selling for about $200
an ounce (28 g),
so being able to get away
with a 20 mg dose
(about 15 cents a day)
rather than a 50 mg dose
(closer to 40 cents a day)
could add up over the long run.
Even smaller doses may work too,
but they just
haven’t been tested.
What about
the tiny pinch over a year
instead of just three months?
Early-stage macular patients
were given 20 mg of saffron
a day for an average
of 14 months
and average visual acuity
improved by two eye chart lines.
They also reported
an improvement in contrast
and color perception,
reading ability,
low-light vision,
and overall quality of life.
The problem is the study
lacked a control group,
so it’s hard to put much stock
in subjective measures
of improvement.
Interestingly, a six-month
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
found no objective
acuity improvement
in either the placebo group
or a 30 mg a day saffron group,
yet reported that the patients
unwittingly in the saffron group
gave subjective reports
of better vision
and general wellbeing.
The researchers suggest
this may be an
antidepressant effect,
and indeed a meta-analysis
of a dozen
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials
of saffron for depression
found it beat out placebo
and was found comparable
to antidepressant drugs.
The largest saffron
vision trial to date
was a double-blind,
placebo-controlled
crossover trial
in which 100 older adults
with mild or moderate
age-related macular degeneration
were randomized to 20 mg
of saffron a day
or placebo for three months,
then switched
to the opposite group
for an additional three months.
When on the tiny
daily pinch of saffron
there was a significant,
yet modest improvement
in visual acuity,
and this was the case
for both those on and off
best practice therapy
(the beta-carotene free
AREDS supplementation),
suggesting an additive benefit.
In our next story,
we look at the effects of both
oral and topical application
of the spice saffron
for male impotence.
The spice saffron has traditionally
been considered an aphrodisiac.
It has been shown to improve Prozac-induced
sexual dysfunction in women and men,
significantly improving
erectile function.
If it works for drug-induced
dysfunction,
might it work for just
regular erectile dysfunction?
Why not just use
pills like Viagra?
They can work, but many men stop
using them due to, for example,
adverse side-effects.
Nearly half of men decide
the cons outweigh the pros.
For men that don’t like
drugs there’s always surgery,
the implantation of
penile prosthetics.
Unbelievably, penile implant usage
evidently dates back to the 16th century.
Early experiments involved
transplanting a guy’s rib cartilage,
or their actual rib
into their penis.
Thankfully space-age
technologies in the 60s
allowed men to keep
their ribcages intact.
Originally the implants left men
in a permanently erect state,
but then the Flexirod was invented
with a hinge in the middle
so the guy could like bend it
down in half for improved concealment.
Of course, proper
sizing is important.
If the implants are too small there
can be drooping at the tip
leading to what’s called a
“supersonic transport deformity.”
Why?
“Because of its resemblance
to the nose of the Concorde” jet.
Whereas “overlong prostheses
can also be a problem,
with the semi-rigid rods
[eroding]” out of the penis.
Although they generally
perforate into the urethra,
the rods can also extrude through
the tip or the shaft.
Ouch.
Now there are inflatable
devices, and perhaps one day
there will be “expandable foams that
respond to external magnetic fields”
or metal mesh technology that could expand
and retract in a cage-like fashion.
And you thought it was hard to
get through airport security now.
There’s got to
be a better way.
Twenty men with erectile dysfunction
were followed for ten days
taking 200 mg of saffron a day—
that’s about a quarter teaspoon—
but first they were brought
into the RigiScan room,
where they were hooked up to a computer
controlled, battery-powered system
for recording of penile tumescence,
meaning swelling and rigidity.
You can hook men up and have
them watch a VHS video tape,
though use of the device is
controversial, described as an
“expensive, complicated, and
time-consuming effort.”
But after the ten days of taking saffron there
did appear to be a significant improvement
in tip and base rigidity
and tumescence.
Whether it’s possible to replace
Viagra-type drugs with this golden plant
will require "further research
with a bigger sample size.”
But it’s not just size that matters,
they didn’t use a control,
so this could have all just
been one big placebo effect.
Finally, though, a head-to-head
challenge—saffron versus Viagra.
Now normally there’s a third
group—a placebo group, as well—
but evidently, they felt
it would be unethical
to let men go 12 weeks
without an effective treatment.
The saffron appeared safer,
significantly fewer side-effects
like severe headaches, hot flushes,
nasal congestion and nausea…
but not effective at all.
So that’s why I never did a video on
the subject—it just doesn’t seem to help.
But maybe it’s because they made the
mistake of taking the saffron orally,
as opposed to rubbing
it on their penis.
The effects of topical saffron
on erectile dysfunction.
About half of middle-aged
men appear to suffer.
So how about a randomized double-
blind placebo-controlled study.
A gel containing 1% saffron,
or instead of saffron,
a gel containing a little golden yellow
food coloring so they looked the same.
Though presumably, half the
penises smelled like paella;
I guess they didn’t
control for that.
“Both groups were trained to rub a pea-sized
amount of the gel on their penis
half an hour before sexual intercourse”
and then were re-assessed a month later.
And, compared to the food coloring gel,
the saffron did lead to significant
improvements in function, and
desire, and overall satisfaction.
They attribute the effects
to a compound in saffron
that evidently enhances nitric oxide
production in the arteries.
But if that’s the case, then
probably better to treat the cause
and prevent the vascular
dysfunction in the first place.
Finally today,
the spice saffron appears to improve both
the emotional and physical symptoms
of PMS, premenstrual syndrome.
Here’s the story.
PMS is “among the most common
health problems reported by women,”
affecting approximately onein three,
and there’s not much
modern medicine has to offer.
Ancient traditional medicine,
though, in Asia and Persia,
used a spice called saffron
to treat menstrual disorders.
But, what did they know?
And, that was 3,500 years ago—
in fact, the earliest recorded
use of any medicinal plant.
Didn’t they know, though,
that you can’t really know anything
unless it’s put through a double-blind,
randomized, placebo-controlled trial?
Well, it took 3,500 years,
but we finally have it.
Women experiencing PMS
for at least sixmonths
were randomly assigned
to a capsule of saffron,
versus a capsule of nothing,
and lo and behold,
“saffron was found to be effective in relieving
symptoms of PMS.”
Check it out.
Reported PMS symptoms
significantly dropped
even within the first cycle,
and continued to improve.
This included changes in “mood
(anxiety, irritability,
depression, nervous tension,
mood swings and
[feelings of being] out of control),
behaviour (poor coordination,
insomnia, confusion,
headache, crying and fatigue),
pain (aches, cramps and tenderness)
and [other] physical [symptoms
including]… craving[s] and swelling)…”
All thanks to a little spice,
from the saffron crocus.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.